Guide to the Time Inc. Life Publishing and Business Records 1936-2001 MS 3009-RG 26
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Life Publishing and Business Records
1936-2001
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 26
31.21 Linear feet in 33 record cartons including 18 reels of microfilm, 3 flat boxes
The Life Publishing and Business Records contain materials from the offices and staff of the business and publishing side of the magazine's operation. The majority of materials come from the publisher, and the advertising sales, business, market research, and circulation departments.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include contracts and consent forms. Restricted boxes include R27 and R42. Materials in box 3317 are sealed due to mold.
Unreformatted audiovisual and digital material in the collection is not accessible.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
This record group is arranged into nine series:
Series I. Publisher's Office Files
Series II. Business Office Files
Series III. Advertising Sales Files
Series IV. Market Research Department Files
Series V. Advertising Copy Acceptance Files
Series VI. Marketing and Sales Files
Series VII. Public Relations Department Files
Series VIII. Circulation Director Files
Series IX. Newsstand Department Records
Historical Note
For the majority of Time Inc.'s existence, the company maintained a strict separation of editorial from the publishing and business side of each magazine, colloquially called the separation of "church" (editorial) and "state" (publishing). Publishing and Business Management includes the publisher, general manager, business manager, advertising sales, marketing services, letters, circulation, and public relations. The editorial side reported up to the editor-in-chief and the publishing/business side reported up to the corporate business executive who was the president prior to 1960 and the chief executive officer after that. Henry Luce structured Time Inc. this way so that the business side could not (in theory) influence the editorial content of the publications. For example, the advertising sales people could not interfere with a magazine's decision to run an article on the dangers of cigarette smoking, even though it might mean losing millions of dollars in tobacco ads.
In February 1936, Luce came up with the idea of creating a picture magazine. Luce proposed his new magazine concept to Time Inc. executives. At first, the group thought that Luce wanted to increase the number of pictures include in Time or that he wanted to add a supplement to the magazine but Luce was adamant that he wanted to create a magazine focused on photo journalism. While the executives were suspicious, Luce knew the idea could work. Luce's faith in the concept came from his experience with Fortune. Fortune, itself, was almost a photo journalism magazine and had been innovative in its use of photography. If these advances could be combined with Time's editorial content, Life could be a success.
After doing some initial research and testing, Time Inc. published the first issue of Life on November 23, 1936. In the original proposal to the board, the magazine would be the same size as the Illustrated London News and printed on shiny paper with around 200 high-quality photographs recording significant current news events including detailed captions. By presenting the images in this fashion, Luce hoped that the reader would be able to both enjoy what they were seeing but also be able to study the images to gain a logical understanding of what was happening in the world around them.
At the magazine's launch, it would cost 10 cents per issue, or $3 per year for a subscription. Based on the price of the magazine, they decided to name it Dime, The Show-Book of the World but quickly decided to change its name. According to Elson, staff and charter subscribers were asked to submit other names, and the title Life was suggested by both cofounder Henry Luce's wife Clare Luce and Time Inc. president James Linen's father. Since the name was already in use by another publication, Luce purchased it in order to acquire the rights.
The first staff members in 1936 were Luce as managing editor, John Martin as Luce's alternate and proposed sucessor as Life's managing editor, Daniel Longwell as picture editor, Alfred Eisenstaedt and Peter Stackpole as staff photographers, and Mary Fraser as copy chief. Despite a strong staff and a good concept, the magazine's financial outlook was ambiguous. Based on their pre-launch research, they knew that circulating the magazine wouldn't be a problem since most readers were attracted by the pictures and wanted to purchase the magazine to find out more. The real problem was figuring out how to turn a profit.
If Life followed the example of magazines like Time and Fortune then the way to make a profit would to be to rely on magazine subscriptions to cover the costs of printing and publication. Because of the high cost for making Life, doing this would make the magazine too expensive for the average reader. Instead of relying on subscriptions, Life would rely on advertising to bring in the needed revenue. With this idea in mind, the money made from the magazine's circulation would be used to cover the cost of printing the magazine but advertising revenue would cover everything else.
During Life's run, it was one of Time Inc.'s most successful ventures in terms of subscriptions and reader response but struggled with production and financing. Even though Life was popular, Time Inc. could not financially sustain production of Life and suspended its production as a weekly magazine in December 1972. Almost as soon as production was suspended, Time Inc. began planning Life's revival. The Magazine Development department published the first Life special in 1973 as a newsstand magazine followed by nine more. Time Inc. revived Life as a monthly in 1978. In 2000, publication was again suspended, but revived in 2004 as a newspaper supplement. In 2007, Time Inc. completely ceased printing of Life and created a website for images from the collection.
Citations:
Elson, Robert T. 1968. Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Publishing Enterprise, 1923-1941. New York: Atheneum.
Hooper, Bill. Email to Holly Deakyne, 10 June 2016.
Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum.
Time To Stop Publishing Life Magazine, Will Keep It Online. U.S. News. CNBC, 26 March 2007. https://www.cnbc.com/id/17797635.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. 2015.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Information about the history of Life and additional records from the editorial offices can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39). Records from the editorial offices are in the Time Inc. Life Editorial Records (MS 3009-RG 9).
Additional files regarding the rights and reproduction of Life photographs are in the Time Inc. Editorial Services Records (MS 3009-RG 47).
Scope and Contents
The Life Publishing and Business Records contain materials from the publishing and business sides of the magazine's operation. The majority of materials come from the publisher, and the advertising sales, business, market research, and circulation departments. The main focus of the collection is on advertiser information, advertising sales, magazine sales, the use of photographs owned by Life, joint ventures between Life and other companies, and with circulation challenges.
Advertising.; Advertising copy; Clippings (information artifacts); Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Marketing research; Public relations; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History; Barnet, Bruce; Drayton, Sandy; Gaeddert, Orlan, 1928-2014; Hintsa, Mark; Ostheimer, Richard H.; Phillips, Nancy; Time, inc. -- Archives.; Time, inc. -- History.
- Series I. Publisher's Office Files, 1955-1971; 5.5 Linear feet in 6 record cartons
  Scope and Contents
  The Publisher's Office Files focus on requests to reproduce photographs and articles from the magazine in other publications. There are additionally a limited number of files regarding exhibits using photographs owned by Life.
  Arrangement
  Arranged into three subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Exhibition Files
  Subseries I.B. Photograph Rights and Reproductions Files
  Subseries I.B. Article and Excerpt Rights and Reproductions Files
  - Subseries I.A. Exhibition Files, 1955-1965; 0.25 Linear feet in 3 folders
    The Exhibition Files includes three folders. The materials in these folders focus on the use of Life photographs in exhibits. These exhibits are not curated by or created by Time Inc. or any of its subsidiaries. Included in this subseries are check requisition forms, clippings, expense reports, list of images to be used in exhibits, notes on exhibit attendance and publicity, pamphlets, photographs, and correspondence. The correspondence included in this subseries was mostly sent to or from Ruth Fowler who was Life assistant publisher and letters department manager from 1960 to 1972. The correspondence discusses photos on loan, the use of paintings and transparencies, licensing for exhibit, and the insurance for photos and paintings. Because of the limited nature of this subseries, it is unclear if these folders were part of Fowler's personal files or belong to some other group of records within the publisher's office.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Illuminations: Exhibit Background, Clearances, etc., 1955-1958 (Offsite-box 3020, Folder 1)
    - Sistine Chapel, 1956-1965 (Offsite-box 3020, Folder 2-3)
  - Subseries I.B. Photograph Rights and Reproductions Files, 1967-1970; 3.25 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
    The Photograph Rights and Reproductions Files contain materials from 1969 to 1970 and focus on the use and reproduction of photographs and images that Life had the rights to. The majority of materials in this subseries are correspondence but there are also routing forms, invoices, photo lab forms, clippings, and photos. The correspondence was mainly sent to and from Vassillia Moore and Ruth Fowler. Moore appears to have worked in the publisher's office, based on documents within the subseries, but it is unclear what position she held and she is not included in any departments heads lists. Fowler was Life assistant publisher and letters department manager from 1960 to 1972. The Correspondence generally contain requests for the use of images, photos, and transparencies as well as requests for reproductions of those materials.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - A, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 3020, Folder 4)
    - A [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - B-H, 1969 (Offsite-box 3020, Folder 5-14)
    - C [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - E [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - F [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - G [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - H [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - H: Harcourt, Brace and World, Inc., 1969 (Offsite-box 3020, Folder 15)
    - H: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Inc., 1969 (Offsite-box 3020, Folder 16)
    - H: Holt, Rinehart, and Winston, Inc [RESTRICTED], 1966 (Offsite-box R42)
    - H: Houghton-Mifflin Co., 1969 (Offsite-box 3020, Folder 17)
    - H: Houghton-Mifflin Co. [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - I-P, 1969 (Offsite-box 3020, Folder 18-25)
    - L [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - M [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - P [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - R, 1969 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 1)
    - R [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - R: Reader's Digest, 1969 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 2)
    - R: Reader's Digest [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - S, 1969 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 3)
    - S [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - S: Silver Burdett and Scott, Foresman, 1969 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 4)
    - S: Silver Burdett and Scott, Foresman [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - USIA (United States Information Agency): Photos, 1969 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 5-7)
    - USIA (United States Information Agency): Scotchprints Text, 1969 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 8)
    - USIA (United States Information Agency): Scotchprints Text [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - V-W, 1969 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 9-10)
    - W [RESTRICTED], 1969 (Offsite-box R42)
    - A, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 11)
    - A [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - American Heritage, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 12)
    - B-C, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 13-14)
    - B-C [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - Crowell-Collier, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 15)
    - D, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 16)
    - D [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - D.C. Heath, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 17)
    - E, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 18)
    - Encyclopedia Britannia, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 19)
    - F, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 20)
    - Field Enterprises, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 21)
    - Field Enterprises [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - G, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 22)
    - G [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - Ginn, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 23)
    - Grolier, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 24)
    - H, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 25)
    - Harcourt, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 26)
    - Harper and Row, 1970 (Offsite-box 3021, Folder 27)
    - Harper and Row [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - Holt, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 1)
    - Horizon, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 2)
    - Houghton, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 3)
    - I-J, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 4-5)
    - J.B. Lippincott, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 6)
    - K-L, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 7-8)
    - Little Brown, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 8)
    - M, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 10)
    - M [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - Macmillan, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 11)
    - McGraw-Hill, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 12)
    - N-O, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 13-14)
    - Prentice-Hall, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 15)
    - Prentice-Hall [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - Q, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 16)
    - Random House, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 17)
    - Rand McNally, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 18)
    - Reader's Digest, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 19)
    - Reader's Digest [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - S, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 20)
    - S [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - Scott Foresman, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 21)
    - Scott Foresman [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - Silver Burdett, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 22)
    - T-U, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 23-24)
    - T-U [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - USIA (United States Information Agency), 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 25-27)
    - USIA (United States Information Agency) [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
    - V-W, 1970 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 28-29)
    - W [RESTRICTED], 1970 (Offsite-box R42)
  - Subseries I.C. Article and Excerpt Rights and Reproduction Files, 1967-1971; 1.75 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
    Includes reprint and reproduction requests from outside sources. The files come primarily from Joan Mueller. Folders in box 3317 are sealed due to mold issues.
    Files remain in the original order.
    - Silver Burdette Company, 1970 (Offsite-box 3316, Folder 1)
    - Magazines, 1967-1971 (Offsite-box 3316, Folder 2-29)
    - High School Publications, 1967-1970 (Offsite-box 3316, Folder 30-32)
    - College Publications, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 3316, Folder 33)
    - College Publications [RESTRICTED], circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3317, Folder 1)
    - Government Publications [RESTRICTED], circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3317, Folder 2)
    - House Organs [RESTRICTED], circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3317, Folder 3)
    - Newspapers [RESTRICTED], circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3317, Folder 4-5)
    - New York Times [RESTRICTED], circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3317, Folder 6)
    - Religious Publications [RESTRICTED], circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3317, Folder 7-8)
    - Miscellaneous [RESTRICTED], circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3317, Folder 9-12)
- Series II. Business Office Files, 1937-2001; 10.97 Linear feet in 15 record cartons
  The Business Office series focuses on Life's finances as well as agreements between Life and other companies. These agreements were about a variety of topics but mainly focus of joint projects or the use of images or characters owned by an outside organization. Included in this series are clippings, cd roms, contact lists, financial statements and reports, notes, lists of photographers and rights, organizational charts, presentations, promotional materials, and correspondence.
  Arranged into five subseries:
  Subseries II.A. Business Manager Nancy Phillips Files
  Subseries II.B. Business Manager Office Files
  Subseries II.C. Business Manager Agreement and Licensing Files
  Subseries II.D. Financial Statements
  Subseries II.E. General Files
  - Subseries II.A. Business Manager Nancy Phillips Files, 1976-2001; 3.25 Linear feet in 6 record cartons
    Biographical Note
    Nancy Phillips began working for Time Inc. in 1987 as the assistant circulation director at People. It is unclear how long she remained in this position before moving to Life. At some point between 1987 and 1993, Phillips began working for Life as magazine's general manager then later became the business manager. Based on her files, Phillips remained with Life through at least 2001. It is unclear what position she held after this or if she remained with Time Inc. at all.
    Business Manager Nancy Phillips's files document the organization of the Life business department as well as the finances of Life during her tenure. The materials that date earlier than 1987 likely were sent to Phillips as references to assist her with her work. Included in her files are budgets, circulation reports, financial statements and reports, lists of staff and responsibilities, organizational charts, quarterly financial analysis presentations, sales presentations, strategic plans, and correspondence. The correspondence included with this subseries discusses advertising rates, taxes, revenue, budgets, financial reports, and staffing. She also has memoranda and reports on the finances of Life Picture Sales sent by Time-Life Syndication within Editorial Services.
    Her files also include some folders from when she worked at People and some records from Discover which may be for comparative purposes.
    Organized alphabetically with arrangement imposed.
    - Discover Circulation: Presentation, Miller, Bob, 1980-1987 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 1-2)
    - Life: Ads sales bonus, 1994-2000 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 3-4)
    - Life: Ads sales bonus [RESTRICTED], 1995-2000 (Offsite-box R42)
      Includes digital material.
      1 computer disc (floppy disk): 3 1/2 in. On label: "Bonus plans 1999. 1999 Bonus Plans-Ad Sales (from Lisa Russo)."
    - Life: Ad sales meeting, 1997 December (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 5)
    - Life: Back-Up: New Formula, 1994-1996 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 30)
    - Life: Book makeup model, undated (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 6)
    - Life: Budget: 1999 Sept/2000 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 7-9)
    - Life Budget Reports: Estimate: 1999 April (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 34)
    - Life Budget Reports: 1999 Estimates, 2000 Budget, and 2001-2003 Strategic Plan (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 35)
    - Life Budget Reports: Financial History, 1995 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 1)
    - Life Budget Reports: Year-End Final Close Schedules: 1999 December, 2000 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 2)
    - Life: Business and budget reviews, 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 10-11)
    - Life: Business Office organization, 1988-1998 (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 31)
    - Life: Circulation leverage-Susan Ferris, 1987? (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 12)
    - Life: Circulation modeling, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 13)
    - Life: Comparative magazine on-sale dates, 1994? (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 14)
    - Life: Conference: Business managers, 1989 November (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 15)
    - Life: Financial history, 1993-1994 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 16)
    - Life: Financials/Comparisons: Other magazines, 1989 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 17)
    - Life: Financials?: Disks, circa 1990 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 18)
    - Life: International Business Channel, 1991, undated (Offsite-box 3022, Folder 32-33)
    - Life: LifeSpan House: Modification Agreement, 2000 (Offsite-box 4184, Folder 19)
    - Life: LifeSpan House: Modification Agreement [RESTRICTED], 2000-2001 (Offsite-box R42)
    - Life: Logan, Don: Presentation, 1992 June (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 19)
    - Life: Logan, Don: Presentation, 1995 August (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 5)
    - Life: Magazine Publishers Association: Financial Analysis, 1993-1998 (Offsite-box 4280, Folder 20)
    - Life: Management Memos, 1976-1981, 2004 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 6)
    - Life Picture Sales: Financials, 1993-1998 (Offsite-box 4184, Folder 17-18)
    - Life: Managers meeting, 1996 March (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 1)
    - Life: Managers meeting, 1997 May (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 2)
      1 computer disc (floppy disk): 3 1/2 in. On label: Basics. Colorado presentation charts."
    - Life: Managers meeting, 1998 November (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 3)
    - Life: OTIP pricing strategy, 1991-1996 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 4)
    - Life: Profits and losses: Travel & Leisure / Food & Wine, 1995? (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 5)
    - Life: Profitability models, 1987 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 6)
    - Life: Publishing formula, 1988-1992 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 7-9)
    - Life Quarterly: 1995 July (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 3-4)
    - Life: Sales presentation, 1996 October (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 10)
    - Life: Simmons: SMRB, 1997 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 12)
    - Life: Simmons Data, 1993-1996 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 13)
    - Life: Space Rates, 1994-1995 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 14)
    - Life: Strategic planning, 1994 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 11)
    - Life: Strategy discussion, 1992 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 12)
    - Life: Supplementary rates and product information, 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 13-14)
    - Life: 13th issue, 1986 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 15)
    - Life: Times: The American Century Project, 1993 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 16)
    - Life: Trim size: 1989 review / 1990 analysis, 1986-1990? (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 17)
    - Life: Weekly background: Magazine Gropu strategic plan, 1990 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 18)
    - People: Ad revenue report, 1991 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 19)
    - People: Circulation, 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 20)
    - People: Effect of changing source mix on demographics research marketing analysis, 1988 (Offsite-box 4281, Folder 21)
    - Picture Week, 1982-1986 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 7-11)
    - Time Inc. Financial Highlights, 1995-1998 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 15-17)
    - Time Inc. Sales and Use Tax Seminar, 1995 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 18)
    - Warner Publisher Services, 1997 (Offsite-box 3023, Folder 19)
  - Subseries II.B. Business Manager Office Files, 1969-1979; 0.35 Linear feet in 2 record cartons